Good morning. Today's דף daf is ע"א Ayin Aleph 71. We're in
the middle of בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer U'moreh. We're dealing with
a lot of rules to limit the circumstances under which they can
occur. I mean, that's the effect of them. Seems also to be
the intent of them. And so one was of course the age,
then we dealt with, you know, only between 13 and 13 and
three months with two pubic hairs etc. Then we dealt with the
issue about like what exactly a certain amount of meat, a certain
amount of wine, and and only if it's being eaten in in
situations that are neutral, that are neither of מצוה mitzvah orientation, nature,
or of עבירה aveira nature. And the גמרא Gemara added and everybody
at the meal has to all be worthless, you know, sort of
good for nothings. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, we're in
the bottom of ע"א עמוד ב', Ayin Amud Bet, about ten lines
from the bottom, אכל מעשר שני בירושלים. achal Maaser Sheni B'Yerushalayim. So
it says, so מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so that
actually is possible to be meat and wine, because you can use
the money to buy meat and wine of wine you could anyway
bring. So it says כיון דאורחיה הוא קא אכיל ליה לא ממשך.
kivan d'orchai hu ka achil lei lo mamshech. Since he's eating it
in a natural way, you know, he's not going to be led
to a, you know, it's not going to be led to a,
you know, to be like an addiction, meaning like since presumably it
has to be eaten, it's interesting that it doesn't just say that
because it's in the performance of doing a מצוה. mitzvah. But you
know, it sort of makes it just more because, you know, because
it's somehow it's done within those types of limits and laws and
rules and parameters, so it's not something that can get carried and
taken like out of hand, which is interesting because it would seem
that it more has to do with like the מצוה mitzvah category
to it. Okay, but anyway, right, I mean the גמרא Gemara before
said כיון דבמצוה קא עסיק לא ממשך. kivan d'bemitzvah ka asik lo
mamshech. So it's interesting it doesn't say that here. Anyway, אכל נבילות
וטריפות שקצים ורמשים, achal neveilot u'treifot shkatzim u'remasim, and if you ate
various types of non-kosher meats, either animals that weren't shechted properly or
that had טריפות treifot or different types of rodents or whatever, so
אמר רבא אכל בשר עוף אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. amar Rava
achal basar of eino naaseh Ben Sorer U'moreh. If you eat chicken,
you're not a בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer U'moreh. You know, that
doesn't, that doesn't have that type of a, it's not red meat,
you know, you need the red meat to sort of be that
more, I guess, you know, sort of what's it called, gluttonous type
of behavior. The גמרא Gemara says והא תנן אכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים
ורמשים נעשה בן סורר ומורה. ve-ha t'nan achal neveilot u'treifot shkatzim u'remasim
naaseh Ben Sorer U'moreh. But our משנה Mishna mentions שקצים ורמשים, shkatzim
u'remasim, which are like rodents and, you know, and like a bugs
or whatever they are. So it sounds like only because it's an
איסור, issur, it's an עבירה, aveira, not because it's not red meat.
So the גמרא Gemara says התם הוא דנעשה בן סורר ומורה, hatam
hu d'naaseh Ben Sorer U'moreh, if you would eat kosher animals that
weren't red meat, presumably you would be a בן סורר ומורה. Ben
Sorer U'moreh. So the גמרא Gemara says כי תנן נמי מתניתין להשלים.
ki t'nan nami matnitin l'hashlim. Our משנה Mishna is talking about that,
you know, that 90% of the amount of the מנה maneh or
the half of the מנה maneh of meat was red meat, and
yet had a little bit, so you could you could have a
little bit of chicken, but most of it has to be the
red meat. Now of course it doesn't tell you exactly what the
proportions are, is it 51% 49% or whatever, but a little it
doesn't have to be 100% red meat, a little bit could be
other stuff, and that little bit could be other stuff has to
be kosher and can't be טרפה. treifa. Okay. אכל דבר שהוא מצוה
ודבר עבירה, achal davar she-hu mitzvah u-dvar aveira, and then generalized it.
What? I don't know. How? I'm not exactly sure. Whatever. If something
of a מצוה mitzvah or something of an עבירה, aveira, so these
that's sort of the general rule of the משנה. Mishna. דבר מצוה,
dvar mitzvah, תנחומי אבלים. tanchumei avelim. So דבר מצוה dvar mitzvah would
be a meal eaten together with the mourners in order to give
comfort to the mourners. דבר עבירה, dvar aveira, תענית ציבור. taanit tzibur.
דבר עבירה dvar aveira like is a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur and
both of those are interesting, because both of those are like mostly
rabbinic contexts, right, not explicitly biblical מצוות mitzvot although before we had
a whole meal that was done for the עיבור החודש, ibur hachodesh,
which clearly wasn't biblical, at least תנחומי אבלים tanchumei avelim for the
רמב"ם Rambam is under the general ואהבת לרעך כמוך. v'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha.
Anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's see, דבר, davar,
sounds like it's the food as opposed to the time. Well, the
food is in this context. It's eaten in a meal that's in
the context of, oh you mean by the דבר עבירה. dvar aveira.
Right, the context same way like what did you eat, not when
did you eat. Yeah, but it's not that the meat is the
דבר מצוה. dvar mitzvah. You're right, in the case of the שקצים
ורמשים shkatzim u'remasim the meat was the דבר עבירה. dvar aveira. But
in the case of like the the eating of the meal of,
you know, of what do you call חבורת מצוה chaburat mitzvah or
עיבור החודש, ibur hachodesh, it wasn't the meat, we're talking about like
בשר מצוה דבר עבירה אכל כל מאכל. basar mitzvah dvar aveira achal
kol maachal. I understand, I'm just saying that that the general principle
is not like it's only eating שלמים, shelamim, you know, מצה בליל
סדר, matzah b'leil seder, it's in the context of a מצוה, mitzvah,
of doing a מצוה mitzvah meal. Okay, so it's the same point
here. So the גמרא Gemara says וטעמא מאי, v'taama mai, what's the
reason? אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says, איננו שומע בקולנו, enenu
shomeia b'koleinu, בקולנו ולא בקולו של מקום. b'koleinu v'lo b'kolo shel makom.
It has to be that he's defied our our orders and not
God's orders. So if it's defying, now again that's interesting, תענית ציבור
taanit tzibur is not exactly בקולו של מקום. b'kolo shel makom. It's
very interesting, quotes the פסוק pasuk here, until now, at least by
the מצוה mitzvah aspect, it's been quoting the idea of whether it's
going to lead a person, you know, to be ממשך, mamshech, to
be commit, you know, lead them astray, lead them to be addicted
to this behavior. Here it makes it a more formal ruling and
I believe the ירושלמי... Yerushalmi... The ירושלמי Yerushalmi applies this also to
why you're not a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh by a
בר מצווה. Bar Mitzvah. איננו שומע בקולנו, Einenu Shomea Bekolenu, meaning the
only—it's the flip of it, meaning the only issue whose obedience is
at stake here is, you know, even if he's violating our commandment,
but if he's fulfilling God's commandment, if he's doing a מצווה, Mitzvah,
that takes it out of the pure issue of, you know, of
defiant parental authority. So either if you're also defying God's authority, it's
like you make it worse but that somehow makes it better then
it's not just about defying parents. It's like the גנב Gannav of—the
person who does the, you know, who steals in public, the גזלן
Gazlan as opposed to the גנב. Gannav. At least he's not hypocritical.
So if you're also defying God's authority, it's not the same. Or,
if you're defying parental authority but doing a מצווה, Mitzvah, so somehow
that also tempers it and makes it not the same. It has
to be something that's basically, the setting is neutral. That seems to
be the best explanation rather than the גמרא Gemara making it about
ממשיך Mamshich or not ממשיך Mamshich or so on. Anyway, but the
interesting thing is that it even includes something here like a תענית
ציבור, Taanis Tzibur, and רש"י Rashi says explicitly אף על גב דלא
עבר אלא על דרבנן, Af al gav d'lo avar ella al de'rabbanan,
and specifically by the תענית ציבור Taanis Tzibur which is rabbinic, it
connects this idea of קולו של מקום. Kolo Shel Mokom. Anyway, moving
on. אכל כל מאכל ולא אכל בשר שתה כל משקה ולא שתה
יין, Achal kol machal v'lo achal basar shasa kol mashke v'lo shasa
yayin, and it doesn't matter whatever type of gluttonous eating you do,
if it's not meat and whatever drinking you do if it's not
wine, it's not a בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer U'Moreh. And based
on the verse, not the biblical verse but whatever, that says, you
know, זולל בשר וסובא יין. Zolel basar v'sove yayin. אכל כל מאכל
ולא אכל בשר לאתויי דבלה קילית. Achal kol machal v'lo achal basar
l'atuyei d'veila kilit. Okay, even if you're eating this type of a—of
a pressed—dates, right dates? Figs? I always get that wrong, I always
get that wrong. Okay, pressed figs, even though presumably, you know, that
according to the גמרא Gemara gets you a little bit high, gets
you a little drunk, okay, nevertheless, I mean it's interesting because the
meat is normally usually not about being drunk, it's the liquid that
is. Okay, but anyway, even though that could be seen as very,
you know, ממשיך Mamshich behavior, behavior that leads to addiction. שתה כל
משקה ולא שתה יין לאתויי דבש וחלב. Shasa kol mashke v'lo shasa
yayin l'atuyei devash v'chalav. It's funny it doesn't mention שכר, Shechar, which
you would most normally think, right? Like liquor. But anyway, even, you
know, wine and milk, which is also supposed to get you like
a little bit drunk. דתניא אכל דבלה קילית ושתה דבש וחלב ונכנס
למקדש חייב. D'tanya achal d'veila kilit v'shasa devash v'chalav v'nichnas l'mikdash chayav.
So if you eat any of those things and go to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, חייב Chayav because that's considered to be, you
know, יין ושכר אל תשת, Yayin v'shechar al tesht, כל מידי דמשכר,
Kol midi d'meshaker, anything that gets you a little bit drunk, even
if it's not wine. And that's true by going into the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash where it's about getting drunk, but it is not
true about what do you call it, about בן סורר ומורה, Ben
Sorer U'Moreh, where it's specifically about this idea of זולל וסובא, Zolel
v'sove, right? Being a glutton and a drunkard or whatever and somehow
that's read specifically in this context. Interestingly about this, I was reading
over יום טוב Yom Tov a תשובה Teshuvah about somebody who wants
to know, you know, the question about let's say somebody makes קידוש
Kiddush on schnapps on יום טוב—first Yom Tov of all, for anybody
who's sneaked out before תקיעת שופר Tekias Shofar to make a little
קידוש Kiddush or whatever. Anyway, you make קידוש Kiddush on schnapps on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, are you then allowed to do ברכת כהנים?
Birchas Kohanim? Because since you can't go and do the עבודה Avodah
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash when you're drunk, even if you're
not drunk by wine, then are you allowed to do ברכת כהנים
Birchas Kohanim and what defines drunk and how much do you have
to drink and so on. It's an interesting מחלוקת. Machlokes. Yes. Well,
תוספות Tosafos shows this is an exception to ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim
on שמחת תורה Simchas Torah and שחרית Shacharis because they think they...
Right, that is true. Okay, but the question is if you even
have a little bit, like the tiniest—like like the one ounce that
people sometimes have for קידוש, Kiddush, is that enough to be a
problem? איננו נעשה בן סורר ומורה עד שיאכל בשר וישתה יין. Eineno
na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh ad she'yochal basar v'yishteh yayin. תנו רבנן, Tano
rabbanan, top of ע"א ע"א, Ayin Aleph Amud Aleph, תנו רבנן אכל
כל מאכל ולא אכל בשר שתה כל משקה ולא שתה יין אינו
נעשה בן סורר ומורה עד שיאכל בשר וישתה יין. Tano rabbanan achal
kol machal v'lo achal basar shasa kol mashke v'lo shasa yayin eino
na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh ad she'yochal basar v'yishteh yayin. So far it's
exactly like our משנה, Mishnah, שנאמר זולל וסובא. Shene'emar zolel v'sove. Glutton
and a drunkard. ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר. V'af
al pi she'ein raya l'davar zecher l'davar. It's not a proof because
it's not coming from a biblical verse, the next verse we're about
to quote, and it's not necessarily, you know, read and only in
those terms. But nevertheless, here's the verse that we rely on: אל
תהי בסובאי יין בזוללי בשר למו. Al tehi b'sovei yayin b'zolelei basar
lamo. Do not be amongst those that are drunkards of wine and,
you know, gluttons of meat. ואומר כי סובא וזולל יורש V'omer ki
sovei v'zolel yurash I think that means. That one who is a
drunkard and a glutton will become poor. יורש Yurash maybe. וקרעים תלביש
נומה. U'keraim talbish numah. And your—and your—and the sleepy one, you know,
will wear garments of torn garments. Wear... what? קרעים, Kerayim, to be
sleepy. What? מנמנם, Minamnem, to be sleepy. Okay. אמר רבי זירא, Amar
Rabbi Zeira, כל הישן בבית המדרש, Kol hayoshen b'beis hamedrash, anybody that
sleeps, you know, in the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash while you're learning,
you know, you put your head down on the table, take a
little nap or whatever, תורתו נעשית לו קרעים קרעים. Toraso na'aseh lo
keraim keraim. Your learning becomes torn into little pieces. You lose continuity
to your learning, you know, you learn... And then you wake up
again and learn five more minutes and fall down or whatever. Anyway,
it breaks it up into little segments and it doesn't become a
whole piece, שנאמר shenemar וקרעים תלביש נומה, ukrayim talbish numa, and torn
garments will be worn by the one who dozes off, who sleeps.
All right. Back to the משנה, mishna, back to בן סורר ומורה.
ben sorer umoreh. גנב משל אביו ואכל ברשות אביו. ganav mishel aviv
veachal birshus aviv. So now, by the way, even if the פסוקים,
psukim, you know, זולל וסובא zolel vesoveh is in the פסוקים, psukim,
okay, you want to limit it specifically to wine and meat, you
want to limit it to certain quantities. At least that's interpreting the
words in the פסוקים. psukim. Now we also introduce this idea that
the boy, the son, stole money. You know, where's that in the
פסוק? pasuk? It says כי יהיה לאיש בן סורר ומורה איננו שומע
בקול אביו ובקול אמו ויסרו אותו ולא ישמע אליהם ותפסו בו אביו
ואמו, ki yihiye leish ben sorer umoreh einenu shomeia bekol aviv uvekol
imo veyisru oso velo yishma aleihem vesafsu vo aviv veimo, right? בננו
זה סורר ומורה איננו שומע בקולנו זולל וסובא. benenu zeh sorer umoreh
einenu shomeia bekolenu zolel vesoveh. All you get is that he's like,
you know, is that he's a זולל וסובא. zolel vesoveh. Where do
you get that he's stealing money? But somehow I guess the חזל
chazal understood because it's, you know, that maybe the סורר ומורה, sorer
umoreh, you know, maybe that's saying more than the זולל וסובא, zolel
vesoveh, you know, maybe the איננו שומע בקולנו einenu shomeia bekolenu also.
There has to be some way in which they're defying parental authority,
not just going ahead and like, you know, eating and drinking and
whatever. Fine. So you're not listening to your parents, you know, you're
not, you know, there's one thing, look, I guess what's worth mentioning
in this context is the idea of כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av
vaeim, you know, where we tell our kids when, you know, we're
raising them is that you gotta listen to your parents. It's a
מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av vaeim. What people never
tell kids at that time, haha, because they don't know, is that
according to pretty much, you know, all the אחרונים, acharonim, it's certainly
not a דאורייתא deoraisa of כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av vaeim to
listen to your parents. It might not even be a דרבנן. derabbanan.
כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av vaeim is not straight—I mean, if you
are disrespectful and defiant of parental authority in general, that's not honoring
your parents. But if you sort of say, well, I very much
respect your opinion, but I'm not going to do that, it more
applies also by adult kids, okay, there's no obligation to listen to
everything your parents tell you. כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av vaeim is
doing acts that are not, one minute, that are not, you know,
not disrespectful of your parents, that's specifically יראה, yira, when the משנה
mishna talks about not disagreeing with them in public. Again, that means
in a way that it's like publicly arguing or defying their authority,
but it does not mean like a strict obligation to listen to,
you know, to everything that they tell you to do. So כיבוד
kibbud is also specifically, you know, sort of service, taking care of
their needs, providing them food and clothing and so on, attending to
them etc. So it's interesting, right, if the parents were to tell
the kid, don't you go ahead and be, you know, stuffing your
face with that meat and hanging out with those good-for-nothings and drinking
that wine or whatever, and he would go ahead and do it,
since it was not directly about the honor of the parents, it
was just about obeying them, it would not be a violation of
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av vaeim. So it could be that that's
why, you know, I'm not saying technically within הלכות כיבוד אב ואם,
hilchos kibbud av vaeim, but within conceptually, חזל chazal understand that there
has to be something that directly sort of, you know, injures the
parents. In order to be a—not just a זולל וסובא, zolel vesoveh,
but a סורר—סורר could be going off the דרך. derech. But a
מורה, moreh, a rebel against your parents, you know, איננו שומע בקולנו,
einenu shomeia bekolenu, I think that's probably why they understood that, you
know, that it has to be something that's stealing from the parents
and not just going ahead and doing this irresponsible behavior. Yes, Micha,
you wanted to say something? Meaning in terms of following, not listening,
hearing. Right, not hearing, obeying. Obeying, right, exactly. Exactly. Okay, so that's
what is introduced here, and it's interesting it never quotes a פסוק
pasuk for this. It just assumes that this context of being זולל
וסובא zolel vesoveh is in the context of having stolen from parents.
גנב משל אביו ואכל ברשות אביו. ganav mishel aviv veachal birshus aviv.
If somebody stole the money from the father and ate in the
father's under the father's, you know, roof. Okay, by the way, it's
mentioned specifically אביו. aviv. We'll see at the end of the משנה
mishna about אמו. imo. It also mentions specifically גנב, ganav, not גזל,
gazal, because although גזל gazal is a bigger act of defiance, one
of the things that's going to interest the גמרא gemara is, is
it ממשיך? mamshich? Is this going to become behavior that's going to
be habitual? You know, and this happens, right? People that have drug
habits, you know, they like, you know, steal from their mother's purse,
you know, go to the father's wallet, they take money. But they
don't do it openly because then they'll be stopped, right? But because
they actually so pilfer, actually, you know. So that's גנב, ganav, right?
It's not an open taking from the parent. Okay, one minute. ואכל
ברשות אביו, veachal birshus aviv, okay, I mean very—but let me finish
the משנה. mishna. Okay, so if it was all in the father's
home, or משל אחרים ואכל ברשות אחרים, mishel acherim veachal birshus acherim,
stole from other people and ate in some other place, whether the
person's home you stole from or some other home, or משל אחרים
ואכל ברשות אביו, mishel acherim veachal birshus aviv, stole from other people
and ate in your father's home, אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. eino
naaseh ben sorer umoreh. None of those cases are בן סורר ומורה
ben sorer umoreh because we'll see, because if the stealing has to
be from the father for it to be accessible money and something
that will become repeat behavior, stealing from other people will not afford.
afraid, but the eating has to be out of the father's home
because eating in the father's home you're afraid you'll get caught, and
therefore it has to be the combination of the money has to
be accessible in the father's home and the eating has to be
in a place where you're not afraid you'll get caught, and that
combination is one in which we say will lead to repetitive behavior.
Much easier to steal from home than from other people even though
there's more people than home. Exactly, exactly. Right, which is totally true.
Okay, עד שיגנוב משל אביו ויאכל ברשות אחרים ad sheyignov mishel aviv
v'yochal birshus acherim until you steal or burgle from the father and
eat somewhere else. ורבי יהודה אומר עד שיגנוב משל אביו ומשל אמו,
v'Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyignov mishel aviv u'mishel imo, since it says
איננו שומע בקולנו, einenu shomea b'koleinu, then therefore it has to be
stealing from both mother and father. It's interesting, right? The pasuk opens
with כי יהיה לאיש בן סורר ומורה, ki yihyeh l'ish ben sorer
u'moreh, focuses on the father, right? And then it says איננו שומע
בקול אביו ובקול אמו. einenu shomea b'kol aviv u'v'kol imo. So presumably,
because A we'll see, it's harder for women within this halakhic system
to own money in general, so it's harder to get the case
of stealing from mother, but also because it maybe opens with איש,
ish, allows the rabbis to speak about the stealing is specifically from
the father. Michal, you wanted to say something? I missed the beginning
of this thing so also בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh seemingly
not a בת? bas? Correct. What was the end of the day
yesterday? Gemara? Yes. Or two days ago, whatever, yes, that is correct.
גנב משל אביו ואכל ברשות אביו ganav mishel aviv v'achal birshus aviv
the Gemara, אף על גב דשכיח ליה בעית. af al gav d'shachiach
lei bias. So even though the money is available, that's the stealing
part, if it's in the father's house, he's afraid that he'll get
caught when he's doing the eating. בעית. bias. משל אחרים ואכל, mishel
acherim v'achal, right? It's like you totally can see this, right? Kids
stealing money from their mother's purse, father's wallet and then going buying
drugs and doing the drugs somewhere else, you do the drugs in
the home you're going to get caught. Okay. משל אחרים ואכל ברשות
אחרים, mishel acherim v'achal birshus acherim, אף על גב דלא בעית, af
al gav d'lo bias, even though you're not afraid of getting caught
because you're eating it outside of the home, לא שכיח ליה, lo
shachiach lei, if you're stealing from others the money isn't readily available
for you so it's not going to lead to repetitive behavior. וכל
שכן משל אחרים ואכל ברשות אביו, v'chol shekein mishel acherim v'achal birshus
aviv, certainly if it's the flip, stealing from others where the money
isn't available and eating in the father's house where you're afraid you'll
get caught. דלא שכיח ליה ובעית, d'lo shachiach lei u'bias, that the
money isn't available and you're afraid. עד שיגנוב משל אביו ויאכל ברשות
אחרים, ad sheyignov mishel aviv v'yochal birshus acherim, the only time you're
chayav is stealing from the father and eating elsewhere, דשכיח ליה ולא
בעית, d'shachiach lei v'lo bias, the money is available and then you're
not afraid you'll get caught. ורבי יהודה אומר עד שיגנוב משל אביו
ומשל אמו. v'Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyignov mishel aviv u'mishel imo. אמו
מנא לה? imo mana lah? Where does the mother have money from?
מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה, mah shekansah isha kanah ba'alah, what a
woman owns her husband owns. So how does she ever own property?
אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא מסעודה המוכנת לאביו ולאמו. amar Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Chanina misuda hamuchenes l'aviv u'l'imo. So there was food because this
is all about wine and meat. So the mother was about to
eat, the meal and he went and he stole the food from
the kitchen from the food that was being brought out to the
mother. I guess not in the mother's presence, it has to be
גנב. ganav. So anyway so even if she doesn't technically own it,
it's still her food in the sense she was going to be
eating from it. ואמר רבי חנא בר מולדא אמר רב הונא אינו
חייב עד שיקנה בשר בזול ויאכל ויין בזול וישתה. v'amar Rabbi Chana
bar Molda amar Rav Huna eino chayav ad sheyikneh basar b'zol v'yochal
v'yayin b'zol v'yishteh. But we said you have to buy meat and
drink wine, which doesn't mean just that the wine and the meat
has to be cheap, the key here is עד שיקנה. ad sheyikneh.
You have to steal money and buy the stuff. Now why is
that clear? Where do we get that from? The Gemara never explained
that. But presumably it's the same idea of repeat behavior. If money
is always available, things to buy and take and sell and then
buy something else. If you're only going to take the meat and
the wine when it's directly immediately available, what type of a home
is it that there's always meat, you know that if you use
the drugs example, it's always easy to steal stuff of value, sell
it and buy drugs. If the person only stole the drugs when
the drugs were directly available, you wouldn't be as concerned about repeat
behavior. How frequently is it that the drugs are immediately available? So
here too money has to be stolen or something of value. Okay,
the irony and then if the person is willing to steal things
of value, sell them or just steal the cash and buy the
wine and meat, then we're afraid of the repetitive behavior. It's almost
like a rebellious that's right there open as opposed to... Oh I
see, because then you're just, like if I'm eating food in my
house it's not as rebellious as stealing something that's owned and selling
it, like I'm really acting like an outsider. Right. That's a good
point. You want to go out and have some wine. That's a
good point. That's a nice point. Right, like even if the parents
say like don't you go to my liquor cabinet and you do,
it's still like food in the house so you're eating. It's not
as much as like, you know, like you're stealing from your parents
and selling it, you're acting really like an outsider, like somebody that's
sort of violating. That's a nice point, that's a good point. Okay,
ואלא, v'ela, so anyway so it can't just be food that was
set aside for the mother and father. אלא אימא מדמי סעודה המוכנת
לאביו ולאמו. ela eima midmei suda hamuchenes l'aviv u'l'imo. Fine, money that
was set aside to buy a nice meal for the mother and
the father and he took that money. So even though technically the
mother doesn't own the money, it's considered stealing from the mother. איבעית
אימא *Ibayit eima* if you want I can say דאקני ליה אחד
ואמר לה על מנת שאין לבעליך רשות בהן *d'akni lei echad v'amar
la al menas she'ein l'baalech reshus bahen*. Okay, just a very interesting
question, right? Can't a woman could possibly own her own property? Somebody
gave her money and said on the condition that your husband that
your, you know, that your husband has no rights to them, not
even the right to eat the usufruct, the right to the פירות
*peiros*. So that would be a case where it would be purely
the woman's property. It's funny, because the woman often also has property
that's her נכסי מלוג *nichsei milog*, that the husband just has the
right to the פירות *peiros*. Why would we consider that to be
something that would be like let's say the woman brought in, you
know, we people joke when they say like a כתובה *kesubah*, oh,
what's he got in a כתובה *kesubah* there, ten camels, twenty sheep?
So let's say the woman brought in like the you know, like
the story about about what do you call יעקב *Yaakov* and עשו
*Esav*, right? Where where רבקה *Rivka* gives him, you know, these goats.
So רש״י *Rashi* there on the חומש *Chumash* says and where'd she
have her own goats to give? How was she not stealing, right?
It says well, this was the conditions of the כתובה *kesubah*, that
that you know, that יצחק *Yitzchak* had to provide her goats on
a regular basis for her food. And so רש״י *Rashi* actually here
too says that part of the reason the food is considered hers,
even in the case where the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* said it was
the meal that was going to be for hers, is because the
husband has a responsibility to provide the food for the wife. But
again, but why can't you have a case where she brings in,
you know, a hundred sheep and the husband has the right of
אכילת פירות *achilas peiros*, but she has title to it, and if
he stole one of those sheep, and slaughtered and ate it or
whatever, I'm not exactly sure why you can't have a case of
a woman having title even though the husband has פירות *peiros*. But
anyway, that's within רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* that you need father and
mother. Again, interesting why do the רבנן *Rabbanan* say only father? Is
it because it's harder to imagine a case of mother? Is it
because the פסוקים Pesukim *pesukim* open up with the idea of כי
יהיה לאיש *ki yihiyeh l'ish*, emphasizing the father? But what's really absent
from all of this is the understanding that you have to be
stealing money, you have to be stealing, where is that? And as
I said, that might just be more in the איננו שומע בקולנו
einenu shomea b'koleinu, *einenu shomeia b'koleinu* or סורר sorer ומורה *sorer u'moreh*.
Okay, it's not enough to be doing this type of, you know,
addictive behavior, there has to be something that's much more, you know,
infiltrating, you know, into or, you know, or attacking parental authority, and
therefore they understand it's this stealing and I very much like Jenna's
point that just taking the food itself doesn't have that same degree
of rebelliousness, yes. Two questions. The woman could, the wife could inherit
money from a relative? Yeah, yeah, that would be similar to my
point about that you could still have title and not the fruit.
And also, before money existed there was a barter economy. Right. So
that, yeah, well, I understand, that's the whole thing with money. Okay,
משנה Mishnah, *mishna*. Yes. If we're concerned about his future behavior, why
wouldn't stealing from others be an indication? Because in the end he's
going to have to steal from others. I guess we're saying that
there's not enough, we haven't seen yet enough behavior that, you know,
enough indicators that would assume that we can sort of predict repeat
offense, you know, because it's an exceptional type of a case. I
mean, you're right, you could say the opposite, you could say if
he's willing to steal from others, we really see he's going down
this bad path. But you know, but it seems more like we
would look at that as an exception rather than as something that,
oh, if he's doing this once, he's going to do it again
and again. Now of course, the question is let's say in your
case, let's say you had a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh.
*ben sorer u'moreh* that stole two dozen times from other people, right?
He was much more rebellious and it was clear it was repeat
and he didn't care about other people, right? Ironically, you're right, it
wouldn't be a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh *ben sorer u'moreh*.
You know, it's a good point, which I hadn't exactly thought through,
but you know, even once it's demonstrated, we have to move on,
even once it's demonstrated, it's repetitive behavior, it's within these parameters where
we can assume even after one event that or one or two
events that it's indicating something that could be that will be repetitive.
Okay, because he's too young when he's stealing from other people, he
doesn't get punished for that either? No, he would, he's בר מצוה
*bar mitzvah*, but he wouldn't be a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer
u'Moreh. *ben sorer u'moreh*, he'd have to give the money back. I
mean, that's also the irony in the תורה Torah. *Torah*, you know,
what's the punishment for stealing? Give it back. As a גזילה *gezeilah*,
and גנבה *geneivah* I guess it's give it back double, you know.
Okay, היה אביו רוצה ואמו אינה רוצה *Haya aviv rotzeh v'imo einah
rotzah*, if the father, you know, wanted to basically bring him to
בית דין Beit Din. *beis din* and prosecute him, אביו אינו רוצה
ואמו רוצה *Aviv eino rotzeh v'imo rotzah*, or the father didn't and
the mother did, אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה eino na'aseh ben sorer
u'moreh. עד שיהיו שניהם רוצים *eino naaseh ben sorer u'moreh ad sheyihyu
shneihem rotzim* until both of them equally sort of want to do
it. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר אם לא הייתה אמו ראויה לאביו
אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה eino naaseh ben sorer umoreh *Rabbi Yehuda
omer im lo haysa imo re'uyah l'aviv eino naaseh ben sorer u'moreh*.
If his mother was not a fitting wife for the father, he's
not a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u’moreh, *ben sorer u'moreh*. Now
this is something we've had before when the תורה Torah *Torah* talks
about remember, the whole issue about the עריות *arayos*, about father's wife,
what constitutes wife, let's say it's his wife only by עבירה *aveirah*.
But the thing here that the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to
discuss is that the that the תורה Torah *Torah* never mentions wife,
the תורה Torah *Torah* only mentions mother and father, so who cares
whether this woman is permissible to his father or not? Yes, you
had a question, Michael? He's basically saying that the will plays a
role. Well, because it says ותפסו בו אביו ואמו *v'safsu vo aviv
v'imo*, right, והוציאו אותו vehotziu oto *v'hotziu oso* etc., so the mother
and father grabbed him. grab him and bring him to the בית
דין. Beit Din So they have to be the ones. It's not
just the act. You see, part of, look, within the context of
the פסוקים pesukim as I said before, it's not just about that
this kid will wind up being abandoned. It's also about the need
to sort of, you know, protect the institution of parental authority. So
it's like, you know, the parents have to be the ones that
are in a position and saying like we feel he is defying
our authority and this is challenging our authority et cetera and they
have to grab him and take him together and make that claim
to the court. Essentially what the parents are saying is we need
you to protect our parental authority, you know, but that's in the
context of the תורה. Torah In the context of חז״ל Chazal which
understand it more like oh he's going down on this bad path,
you're right, like why does it require the parents to be doing
it together once we can and both of them? Once we can
see that that, you know, part of it might be that if
they're both doing it together it shows it all along he's been
defying their joint authority. You know often the way things work in
a family is you know one person will be the one that
lays down the law of the rule and the other just says
you know go talk to your mother or go talk to your
father whatever it is. So part of what the think here is
not just that the parents needing to protect their authority, but the
reality of him defying like איננו שומע בקולנו, einenu shomea b'koleinu, right?
Defying the authority of both of them is reflected in the fact
that both of them are now coming to בית דין. Beit Din,
If only one was coming to בית דין Beis Din then he
probably didn't really defy the other person's authority. You know that seems
to be how we're reading it. Yeah. And that's... make it super
strong, like in an area that we spoke about how whatever the
women don't have power, there's all these issues. Here, if the mom
doesn't want this... Right, exactly. She can't do anything. Exactly. It is
both of them working in unison and that we're going to see
as we continue. So let's take a look. Okay, מאי אינה ראויה?
Mai einah reuyah? What does it mean not fit for the father?
אילימא חייבי כריתות וחייבי מיתות בית דין, Ilema chaivei krisot vechaivei misot
Beit Din, a woman that's forbidden to the father, you know, his
sister or something like that, so סוף סוף אבוה אבוה נינהו ואמיה
אמיה נינהו. sof sof avuh avuh ninhu v'imei imei ninhu. It never
says anywhere here they have to be married, it just says mother
and father. So even if the kid is like, you know, is
born out of this forbidden union, he's a ממזר, mamzer, whatever the
case might be, it's still father and mother. אלא בשווה לאביו קאמר.
Ella b'shaveh l'aviv ka'amar. It must mean that he says that she
has to be equal to the father. What does equal to the
father mean? תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, so a ברייתא Braita
will clarify. רבי יהודה אומר אם לא היתה אמו שווה לאביו בקול
ובמראה ובקומה אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. Rabbi Yehuda omer im lo
hayta imo shavah l'aviv b'kol u'v'mareh u'v'komah eino na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh.
If she doesn't have the same voice, the same height, and the
same appearance as the father he's not a בן סורר ומורה. ben
sorer umoreh. Sounds like it's the שעיר המשתלח, sa'ir hamishtaleach, you know,
the שני שעירים, shnei se'irim, right? The שעיר לעזאזל sa'ir l'azazel and
the שעיר sa'ir for the, you know, to be brought to the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. They have to be exactly the same in
מראה mareh and קומה komah et cetera. Okay, so אינו נעשה בן
סורר ומורה. ben soreir umoreh. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
דאמר קרא איננו שומע בקולנו. d'amar kra einenu shomea b'koleinu. So their
voice has to be a shared voice. Okay, מדקול בעינן שווה מראה
וקומה נמי בעינן שווה. m'd'kol ba'inan shaveh mareh v'komah nami ba'inan shaveh.
And since the voice has to be the same, height and appearance
also need to be the same. Now what sense does that make?
I mean, it's one thing that the verse says קול, kol, where
do you get height and appearance? So the מהרש״א Maharsha has a
very nice explanation. The מהרש״א Maharsha was also bothered with like what's
the logic behind any of this, not just where do we learn
it out from. And the מהרש״א Maharsha says the point that we
were just saying, that the son has to defy both mother and
father's authority. So if they had a, wait a minute, how does
he do this again? Oh, it's a little, it's a little like
reverse what you would have thought, but he says like this. He
says if they had different voices or they looked different, then we
would say when they brought the kid to בית דין, Beis Din?
we would say we're going to assume that he really was only
like, you know, disobeying one of you. Why? Because we're going to
assume that if both of you had, and this is a little
strange but anyway, if both of you had laid down the letter
of the law and were equally sort of saying you're not allowed
to do this, no good, no kid would have ever defied both
of the parents. Okay, so therefore we refuse to believe that it
actually happened. However, if you both look the same and sound the
same or whatever, then we could believe that he defied you. Why?
Because in his mind he always thought it was just one of
you and not the other one. It's a little funny since he
would have, you know, assumed it was all the same parent who
was telling him he was willing to defy, but we're not willing
to assume that he would defy both parents. It's a little, it's
a little complicated the way he does it, but what's interesting is
that he wants to make it, going back to the פסוק, pasuk,
איננו שומע בקולנו, einenu shomea bekolenu the sense of you know it
has to really be a defying of both parents. So the way
to more translate this a little metaphorically of the same voice doesn't
mean that they actually sound the same. I'm not saying this is
פשט pshat in the גמרא. Gemara. I'm just saying that I think
it's what it's getting at, is that they have to be operating
in unison, right? And you often get cases like this where like
you know whatever one of the parents will say, the father will
say like I really think you can go but you know. גמרא,
Gemara I'm just saying that I think it's what it's getting at
is that they have to be operating in unison, right? And you
often get cases like this where like, you know, the whatever, one
of the parents will say, the father will say like, I really
think you can go, but you know your mom's the boss, right?
So that's not operating in unison, right? I mean, some parents are
always מפריד, mafrid, like you know, like I don't know, somebody says
the scene from the Godfather pops into my head where one point
he says like, you know, and he and whatever like, you know,
we never, you know, we never argue in front of other people,
right? Whatever, to other people we always have to present like this
unified front, right? So parents, you know, so if the parents really
have to present a unified front to the kid and he has
to defy both of them. So they have to be operating in
the same voice, the same appearance, the same whatever. If the parents
are like a little bit not unified, you know, even if the
father is saying like, listen to your mother, I really think it's
okay, but listen to your mother, right, then he's not really defying
both of them. To defy both of them means that they're both
speaking in the same voice. So that's what I really think is
being, you know, is what it's getting at over here. Is there
something between them? That makes a lot of sense, I'm reading the
גמרא. Gemara I think the, I think the גמרא Gemara does, isn't,
what I'd like to believe is the גמרא Gemara is taking that
conceptual idea and translating that into very like, like very literally, okay,
but that what's behind that literal idea is the conceptual point that
only when the parents are really operating, you know, as a unit.
Plus also they have to do everything they can before they turn
the kid to the community, deal with him. Right, right, that's a
good point too. Right, if they're not speaking in a unified voice
then they can't come to us, right? I mean, if that's flipping
the point, but either way, either the kid hasn't really defied them
to, you know, to their power, right, exactly. Okay, so okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, k'man azla ha
detanya, who's it going like that which we taught? Famous thing that
everybody's heard בן סורר ומורה לא היה ולא עתיד להיות. ben sorer
u'moreh lo haya v'lo asid lihyot. בן סורר ומורה ben soreir umoreh?
never was and never will be. ולמה נכתב, v'lama nechtav, why was
it written? דרוש וקבל שכר derosh v'kabel sachar interpret it and get
reward. כמאן? k'man? כרבי יהודה, k'Rabbi Yehuda, it's going like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda. who says how you gonna get parents that look the
same and sound the same, etc.? Okay, now again the way the
מהרש"א Maharsha reads it is, is not just like oh this physically
wouldn't ever happen. The way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it is, if
parents are speaking or the way I'll read it through whatever, the
way I just said with the help of the מהרש"א, Maharsha, if
parents are really speaking in a unified front, in a unified voice,
you'll never have a kid that will defy both parents when they're
speaking, when they are that much like in their, you know, shared
in their, in a singular voice, okay. So at least I would
hope that would be true. But okay, anyway, so okay, it's like,
it's like רבי יהודה. And that's by the way because the מהרש"א
Maharsha says like what's the דרוש וקבל שכר? derosh v'kabel sachar? If
it never will happen, then what are we supposed, what are we
learning from it and why did the תורה Torah write it? So,
you know, he said that the תורה Torah sort of wrote it
to teach you that, you know, if your kids are going off
or whatever, it's probably because you're not speaking to them in a
shared, you know, in a shared voice. If you, if you present
a very clear message and a common front to your kids, you
know, these types of things will not happen. That's the way the
מהרש"א Maharsha reads it, which, you know, I can't say is a
hundred percent the פשט, pshat, but anyway, but it would certainly help.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעית אימא רבי שמעון
היא iba'it eima Rabbi Shimon hi or it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
דתניא, detanya, it was taught in a ברייתא braitah אמר רבי שמעון:
amar Rabbi Shimon: וכי מפני שאכל זה תרטימר בשר ושתה חצי לוג
יין איטלקי, vechi mipnei she'achal zeh tartimar basar veshahta chatzi log yayin
italki, just because this guy ate like a certain amount of meat
and drank a lot of this Italian wine, so הרי אביו ואמו
מוציאין אותו לסקלו, harei aviv v'imo motzi'in oto l'saklo, the parents will
take him to get him stoned? אלא, ella, it can't be, it
can't be what the תורה Torah is asking us to do. אלא
לא היה ולא עתיד להיות, ella lo haya v'lo asid lihyot, it
won't be and it will never be. ולמה נכתב, v'lama nechtav, why
was it written? דרוש וקבל שכר derosh v'kabel sachar get reward. Now
the question is I don't understand, he's asking this isn't fair just
because the guy ate some meat and drank some wine. But why
does that mean it will never happen? Who's to prevent it from
happening? It's not like they have to look the same and sound
the same according to this. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says and you
have to read the גמרא Gemara carefully, it's not that is it
fair that the, that the תורה Torah, says to stone him just
because he did this? Notice what he says. Just because he ate
this meat and drank this wine, do you think that the father
and mother would bring him to בית דין Beis Din to stone
him? So the question is, going back to our משנה, mishna. like
what parents would ever do that? Just because a kid is a
little misbehaving? You think that that would motivate parents? Like what type
of parents would you have to be that you would want to
bring your kid to get stoned in בית דין? Beis Din So
he's not saying it's impossible for it to happen, he's just saying
like he can't imagine any parents that would actually do such a
thing, okay. And but so what's the דרוש וקבל שכר? derosh v'kabel
sachar? The דרוש וקבל שכר derosh v'kabel sachar is to tell you
that while it's true that parents would have רחמנות rachmanos on their
kid, the תורה Torah is teaching you why is the תורה saying
stone him? Remember because of this message that the kid is going
down a, down a bad path and he's going to wind up
leading, living a life of crime. So even though parents will never
bring him to בית דין Beis Din to get him stoned, they
should take heed from the point about what the תורה is saying
and they should know that they better start putting their foot down
or this kid is going to real, you know, you know, live
a life of, you know, a, you know. of crime and go
off of the straight and narrow. So there's a very nice line
that the מהרש"א Maharsha says, I'll just read you the last line
here. He says: He says like this. He says: הן ודאי לא
יגיע לסוף דעתו ויחוס עליו. Hen vadai lo yagia l'sof da'ato v'yachos
alav. Who what parents would ever think oh he's definitely going to
be this abandoned and let's get him killed? No, they'll have compassion
on him. Parents, parents would never do such a thing. ועל כן
לא היה ולא עתיד להיות, V'al kein lo hayah v'lo asid lihyos,
שאביו ואמו לא יגיעו לסוף דעתו ויחוסו עליו She'aviv v'imo lo yagiu
l'sof da'ato v'yachusu alav because the parents will have רחמנות, rachmanus, that's
why it won't happen. But he says, אלא למה נכתב Ella lamma
nichtav so why was it written? אלא דרוש Ella derosh you're supposed
to interpret it. שאביו ואמו She'aviv v'imo the father and mother have
to pay attention to this פרשה, parsha, not us in the בית
מדרש. Beis Medrash. ודרשו V'dershu and they should learn from this, שהתורה
הגיעה לסוף דעתך. She'haTorah higiah l'sof da'atcha. The Torah is telling you
a lesson. Hey, we know you're going to have compassion. But you
should know that we're saying here that this kid is fit to
be killed and he is really, if you don't start putting your
foot down, they're going to be a drug addict and it's going
to be a criminal and so on. And the lesson they should
take is, fine, don't get him killed, אבל על ידי זה יוכיחו
ויסרו את בניהם ויקבלו על זה שכר. Aval al yedei zeh yochichu
v'yisru es bneihem v'yekablu al zeh sachar. That's the קבלת שכר. kabbalas
sachar. Start being good parents, start laying down the letter of the
law, start showing a little tough love, and then you'll get the
שכר sachar because then you'll get your kid back to the straight
and narrow. Okay, and then he says like this. And now he
has a little... it's very funny. Sometimes in the... sometimes he adds
a little contemporary commentary. So here's what he says: אבל בזמן הזה
אינו שים לב לזה. Aval bazman hazeh einu sam leiv l'zeh. דכל
אחד מחפה על בנו. D'chol echad mechapeh al bno. Nowadays no parents
are really trying to lay down the letter of the law with
their kids and they're all just going soft on them. אף שהוא
באמת חייב מלקות ומיתת בית דין. Af shehu be'emes chayav malkos umisas
Beis Din. They do terrible things, the kids. ואין מוכיחים אותם V'ein
mochiachin osam and parents don't bother, you know, giving them מוסר. mussar.
הנערים הולכים רוב ימיהם בביטול תלמוד תורה. Hana'arim holchim rov yameihem b'vittul
Talmud Torah. והמיני פרק כל כתבי לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שביטלו
תינוקות של בית רבן. V'hameini perek Kol Kisvei lo charvah Yerushalayim ella
bishvil shebitlu tinokos shel beis rabban. So it doesn't sound like they're
criminals, it sounds like they're not spending enough time in the בית
מדרש. Beis Medrash. But anyway, the מהרש"א, Maharsha, he's an opportunity about
how parents have to... a little tough love. Okay? So that's the
דרוש וקבל שכר. derosh v'kabel sachar. We know you won't do it.
You'll have רחמנות. rachmanus. But do more than you're doing, because your
kid is about to lead, you know, is going down the wrong
path. Yes. When did the מהרש"א Maharsha live? 18th century I think.
Somebody can do a quick Google search. Really nothing new under the
sun. Exactly. Okay. Well, it's already in the תורה, the kids who
are rebelling. Okay, fine. Moving on. Okay. Now that we're saying things
that never happened, let's keep on going. ולמה נכתב דרוש וקבל שכר.
V'lamma nichtav derosh v'kabel sachar. אמר רבי יונתן אני ראיתי. Amar Rabbi
Yehonasan ani ra'isi. What are you talking about? I saw a בן
סורר ומורה. ben soreir umoreh וישבתי על קברו. V'yashavti al kivro. I
actually sat on his grave. I saw him and he was stoned
and the whole thing happened. Okay. כמאן אזלא הא דתניא. K'man azla
ha d'tanya. Now we're talking about that, yes, when did the מהרש"א
Maharsha live? 1555. 1555? I didn't realize he was so early. 16th
century? Wow. Yeah, 1555 to 1631. I think... he was related to
the Rav of Prague? The מהרש"א. Maharsha. I don't know, maybe. His
the א aleph of his name, Edels or something, was his mother-in-law
because they... because she supported him. So yeah, exactly. Okay. I see.
Okay. כמאן אזלא. K'man azla. Okay, fine. כמאן אזלא הא דתניא. K'man
azla ha d'tanya. Who does it go like, where she taught: עיר
הנדחת לא היתה ולא עתידה להיות. Ir Ha'nidachas lo haysah v'lo asidah
lihyos. It will never be a city that will all be worshipping
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ולמה נכתבה דרוש וקבל שכר. V'lamma nichtavah derosh
v'kabel sachar. Receive... now it doesn't tell you why it won't happen.
It won't happen that you'll never get a whole city that will
leave, you know, the faith so much to be עובד עבודה זרה.
oved avodah zarah. I don't know, in the period of the בית
ראשון, Bayis Rishon, everybody was being עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah.
Maybe you won't have the combination of a בית דין Beis Din
that's willing to punish for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You know, everybody's
עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah when the... you know, that's what
the פסוקים psukim always say. איש הישר בעיניו יעשה, Ish hayashar b'einav
ya'aseh, אין מלך בישראל. ein melech b'Yisrael. There was no central authority,
that's why everybody was being עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. You
might not have the combination of a בית דין beit din that's
really treating עבודה זרה avodah zarah so seriously and a whole city
willing to worship it. Okay. Or maybe the... you... like we said
before about the parents, you won't have a בית דין beit din
that's willing to go through with this and to actually, you know,
prosecute the whole city. אלא למה נכתב, Ella lamma nichtav, why was
it written? ולמה נכתב דרוש וקבל שכר. V'lamma nichtav derosh v'kabel sachar.
Who is it go like? רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא D'tanya we
taught a ברייתא. braysa. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: כל שיש
בה אפילו מזוזה אחת אינה נעשית עיר הנדחת. Kol sheyesh bah afilu
mezuzah achas einah na'asis Ir Ha'nidachas. So now, here we're saying not
for the reasons I just said, but for technical reasons like the
answer before about the technical reasons about the size, parents looking alike.
As long as there's one מזוזה mezuzah on one doorpost, you can't
make it into an עיר הנדחת. Ir Ha'nidachas. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? אמר קרא, Amar k'ra, the verse says: ואת כל
שללה תקבץ אל תוך רחבה, V'es kol shelalah tikbotz el toch rechovah,
gather all the property in the middle of a רחובה, rechovah, ושרפת
באש V'sarafta ba'eish and burn it. וכיון דאיכא מזוזה לא אפשר. V'keivan
d'ika mezuzah lo efshar. But if there is one מזוזה, Mezuzah, you
can’t gather all of the property of the town, you’re not allowed
to burn the מזוזה. Mezuzah. דכתיב, Dich’tiv, it says, לא תעשון כן
לה' אלהיכם. Lo ta’asun ken l’Hashem Elokeichem. So therefore you won’t make
it an עיר הנדחת. Ir HaNidachat. Now, does that mean that you
won’t, fine, you won’t burn the city, but maybe you’ll still execute
everybody in the city, right? Is maybe it’s just talking about burning
the city? So the גמרא Gemara says, or maybe not, maybe that
would change, I don’t know, everybody individually would be חייב מיתה. chayav
mita. The question is, is there anybody who’s getting killed in the
עיר הנדחת Ir HaNidachat that wouldn’t get killed if they were individuals?
This is a major debate of the רמב"ם Rambam and the רמ"ה,
Ramah, right? The תורה says you destroy all the property and you
kill all the people and the גמרא Gemara says, and everybody who
wasn’t עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara goes free. So is there
anybody you’re killing who’s innocent? So the רמב"ם Rambam says, yeah, you
know who you’re also killing while you’re wiping out the whole city?
All the wives and the kids. Because apparently the people that we’re
talking about are the men. So if the majority of the men
are עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avoda zara, it becomes an עיר הנדחת,
Ir HaNidachat, the innocent men and their families go free and the
wives and the kids get killed. That’s what רמב"ם Rambam says, executed.
The רמ"ה Ramah is like, it’s like, you know, whatever, he’s he’s
he’s shocked, he’s, you know, he’s horrified at that suggestion. But anyway,
but assuming that you’re only killing the perpetrators, so okay, individual maybe
you would still kill them, every individual would still have been an
עובד עבודה זרה, oved avoda zara, but you wouldn’t turn the whole
city into an עיר הנדחת Ir HaNidachat by destroying everything in the
city. For the רמב"ם Rambam again, the bigger חידוש chiddush might, the
question is if you’re not burning the city, would it also mean
that you wouldn’t kill the families of those who had perpetrated the
sin? So you say you have to kill the wives and the
children of the men who were the perpetrators? No, no, no, the
men who were innocent and their families go free, but the men
who were the perpetrators and their families get killed. That’s the way
רמב"ם Rambam reads it. Okay, so if it’s not an עיר הנדחת,
Ir HaNidachat, maybe the families would also be spared according to the
רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay, דכיון דאיכא מזוזה לא תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם. D’keivan
d’ika mezuzah lo ta’asun ken l’Hashem Elokeichem. אמר רבי יונתן Amar Rabbi
Yonatan said רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, no, אני ראיתיה וישבתי על תלה,
Ani re’itiha ve’yashavti al tilah, I saw a city that had been
burned down and I sat on its, you know, on the mound.
Okay, כמאן אזלא דתניא, Keman azla d’tanya, who’s it going like that
which we taught? בית המנוגע לא היה ולא עתיד להיות. Bayit hamenuga
lo haya velo atid lihiyot. A house that has צרעת tzara’at will
never be. Now, that’s not something that offends our moral sensibilities, right?
So this is, you know, you could say we sort of went
from things that are, you know, the the certainly by the case
of the בן סורר ומורה, ben soreir umoreh the גמרא Gemara explicitly
raises the question of where is the justice? By the עיר הנדחת
Ir HaNidachat it doesn’t raise the question, but for many of us
it challenges our moral sensibilities. The בית המנוגע bayit hamenuga is okay,
whatever, but no, that also didn’t happen, so not so it’s not
really making a moral point here. ולמה נכתב, Velama nichtav, it’s just
making a point that some of these things are said just for
the theoretical point. דרוש וקבל שכר. Derosh ve’kabel sachar. Who’s it going
like? כמאן כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Keman k’Rabbi Elazar b’Rabbi Shimon, דתניא
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, D’tanya Rabbi Elazar b’Rabbi Shimon omer, לעולם
אין הבית טמא בית המנוגע Le’olam ein habayit tamei bayit hamenuga until
שיראה כשתי גריסין, she’yira’eh kishtei gerisin, it has to be like the
size of two lentil beans, because the size of a צרעת tzara’at
is one lentil bean. על שתי אבנים al shtei avanim on two
stones, בשני כותלים bishnei kotlim on two different walls, בקרן זוית bekeren
zavit in a corner. So basically what you have is, right, so
if this is, I don’t know, this is like a top view,
right? I mean whatever, here’s the, now I have to draw three-dimensional.
Whatever, I’m not going to draw three-dimensional. Okay, this is the top
view, so it has to be one leprous spot that goes like
this. Okay, it’s on two stones, it’s a combined leprous spot, and
each on each stone it has to be the size of a
נגע צרעת, nega tzara’at, the size of a נגע צרעת nega tzara’at
is one lentil bean. So if it’s on two stones, it’s two
lentil beans wide by one lentil bean high. Okay, so yes, some
says it’s a larger bean than a lentil. Okay, whatever. What bean
does he say it is? A פול השלומי pul hashelomi bean. There
you go. Fine, not a, a fava, that’s it, a fava bean.
Fava bean, okay. Man, how did I get that wrong? I mean
everybody knows fava beans are so different than lentil beans. Right, some
people say lentil. Do you say lentil? At least it’s a bean,
or some people say the amount that four of your hairs on
your right, I thought they said nine, all right, yeah, all right,
moving on, six by six hairs, right? All right, moving on, okay.
All right, moving on, בשני כותלים בקרן זוית, bishnei kotlim bekeren zavit,
ארכו כשתי גריסין, orko kishtei gerisin, it’s two גריסין gerisin long, ורחבו
כגריס, verochbo kegris, it’s one גריס geris wide. מאי טעמא דרבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Mai ta’ama d’Rabbi Elazar b’Rabbi Shimon, what’s his reason? כתיב
קיר וכתיב קירות, Ktiv kir u’ktiv kirot, it says on the wall
and it says walls. איזו קיר שהוא כקירות הוי אומר זה קרן
זוית, Eizu kir shehu kekirot hevei omer zeh keren zavit, what wall
is like walls? It can be said it’s a corner. תניא אמר
רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק, Tanya amar Rabbi Elazar b’Rabbi Tzadok, מקום היה
בתחום עזה, Makom haya bitchum Azza, there was a place in the
within the boundary of עזה, Azza, I guess outside of the city,
והיו קורין אותו חורבתא סגירתא, vehayu korin oto churbata sagirta, they called
it the the waste the the dump of the of צרעת, tzara’at,
that’s where they were the dump of חורבתא churbata is like חורבה,
churva, right, ruins, thank you, the ruin of צרעת, tzara’at, presumably that’s
where they would go ahead and they would dispose of the, either
they they had destroyed a house or, but you didn’t destroy the
house, you just removed the stones. So presumably that’s where they would
they would dump the stones from the house of צרעת. tzara’at. So
actually it did happen. But yes, or maybe it sounds like they
knocked down a whole house. אמר רבי שמעון איש כפר עכו. Amar
Rabbi Shimon ish Kfar Akko. פעם אחת הייתי הולך לגליל paam achat
hayiti holech la-Galil once I went to the Galilee וראיתי מקום שמציינים
אותו veraitti makom shemetzaynin so a place that was designated ואמרו אבנים
מנוגעות פינו פינו לשם veamru avanim menugaot pinu pinu lesham this is
a place where they have stones with צרעת tzaraat don't go there
because you'll become טמא tame you'll walk over them and so on.
Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna So that
is the same thing that it never happened, but it didn't never
happen is just to point that again חז"ל chazal tried to minimize
it because of the moral issue. The last point about צרעת tzaraat
wasn't a moral issue. I mean there's some technical issues but I
think the read of the גמרא Gemara number one that it's not
that it's not possible but that meaning what type of parents would
do such a thing? We can't imagine the parents would do it
and also sort of like the larger lesson about speaking with a
unified front and so on that the מהרש"א Maharsha speaks about or
the balance between the compassion that parents will have for their kids,
you know, and they obviously won't do the harshest punishment, right? These
are these questions of course nowadays like just I mean it's other
people's safety at stake, right? When parents like a kid turns out
to be doing plotting some terrorist plot or whatever, will the parent
turn them into the police and so on? How do you strike
that balance between okay, you're not going to want to get your
kid killed but you have to, you know, but too much love
is not, you know, you need tough love if you want to
care for your kid and certainly protect other people. So figuring out
how to strike that balance, I think that's a very powerful read
of the מהרש"א. Maharsha. Yes. Do we pay attention to רבי יונתן's
Rabbi Yonatan opinion here or actually his multiple opinions? I don't know,
you're right, I mean he's giving direct evidence. Ah, what do you
know? It never happened. Okay, moving on. היה אחד מהם גידם hayah
echad mehem gidam if one of them was did not have did
not have their arms, I don't even know what an English word
for that would be, או חיגר o chiger or lame with not
able to walk well, או אילם o ilem or mute, או סומא
o suma or blind, או חירש o cheresh or deaf, אינו נעשה
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh, if one of the parents was
this way. שנאמר ותפשו בו אביו ואמו sheneemar vetofsu bo aviv veimo
they grab hold of him. ולא גידמין velo gidmin if they don't
have their arms they can't grab hold of them. והוציאו אותו they
bring him out. ולא חיגרין velo chigrin if they're lame then they
can't just bring them out on their own, you know, on their
own mobility there. ואמרו בנינו זה veamru bneinu zeh and they say
בנינו זה bneinu zeh this our son. ולא אילמין velo ilmin they
can't be mute. בנינו זה bneinu zeh this our son, ולא סומין
velo sumin this means they're like pointing and identifying him, they can't
be blind. איננו שומע בקולנו einenu shomea b'kolenu he doesn't listen to
us. ולא חירשין velo chirshin they can't be deaf. Now how do
you know? Because if they're deaf, even if they're able to speak
clearly, you won't be able to tell whether he's really listening or
not listening. I mean I know often you can tell by body
language, but somehow you have to be able to hear that he's
defying or else you assume that maybe he was actually listening. Okay,
מתרין בו בפני שלושה ומלקים אותו. matrin bo bifnei shlosha umalkin oto.
Now you give him warning in front of three and then you
give him lashes because they learned from the פסוק pasuk it says
ויסרו אותו. veyisru oto. They said that they should like, you know,
how do you translate ויסרו? veyisru? They should afflict him, I mean
I'd say the word, but anyway, both mean that they warn him,
don't do this behavior, and it means that they actually gave him
lashes for doing that behavior. Okay, so the sense is, is that
basically they said, you know, the son went ahead and they said,
you know, and he stole from the parents and he ate this
meat or whatever, they brought him to the court and they said,
here's what our son did, he stole, he ate, blah blah blah,
and then they say don't you ever do this again, etc., and
they give him lashes, and then if he does it again, okay,
then he actually becomes a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u'moreh. So
he essentially has to do it twice. What's not exactly clear is
that first act, right? When did they warn him? Right? Is it
כי יהיה לאיש בן סורר ומורה איננו שומע בקול אביו ובקול אמו
ויסרו אותו ולא ישמע אליהם. ki yihyeh le-ish ben sorer umoreh einenu
shomea bekol aviv uvekol imo veyisru oto velo yishma aleihem. Right? So
anyway, it's not exactly clear like when that first eating of the
meat and the drinking of the wine and so on, was he
warned not to do that. Yeah, you have steal, you know, eat
and drink, right? And then, then here you have lashes, and then
if it goes steal, eat and drink and they bring him again,
okay, this is ויסרו אותו. veyisru oto. ויסרו אותו ולא ישמע אליהם,
veyisru oto velo yishma aleihem, right? And then ותפשו בו vetofsu bo
he does it again, which isn't in the פסוק, pasuk, I guess
the ולא ישמע velo yishma is this, he doesn't listen to them
again, and then it's ותפשו בו vetofsu bo and then it's ותפשו
בו vetofsu bo and then you get him and then you stone
him. Okay, so and this presumably is כי יהיה לאיש בן סורר
ומורה איננו שומע בקול אביו ובקול אמו. ki yihyeh le-ish ben sorer
umoreh einenu shomea bekol aviv uvekol imo. So he's not even a
זולל וסובא zolel vesoveh here, you know, but they do say בנינו
זה. bneinu zeh. So somehow like we have to assume that the
איננו שומע einenu shomea that appeared before this was similar to the
זולל וסובא zolel vesoveh down here. Right? But how much is this
taking place after having been warned or not having been warned? He's
just going ahead and doing that. I'll read you the רמב"ם, Rambam,
it's not so clear. I'll read you the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם
Rambam says בנינו זה סורר ומורה, bneinu zeh sorer umoreh, מביאין שני
עדים שגנב משל אביו וקנה בשר mevi'in shenei edim sheganav mishel aviv
vekanah basar blah blah blah ואכל אכילה veachal achilah זו היא העדות.
zu hi ha-edut. There was no call yet, they weren't yet telling
him anything. He just did these acts of defiance. Then they give
him lashes and from the וייסרוהו veyisruhu it says, okay, וייסרוהו, veyisruhu,
חזר וגנב, chazar veganav, אביו ואמו מביאים אותו לבית דין, aviv ve'imo
mevi'im oto l'veit din, ומביאים שני עדים, umevi'im shnei eidim, ומעידים שאכל
ושתה, ume'idim she'achal veshotah, ואמרו בתורה, ve'amru b'torah, אחר שהתרו בו, achar
she'hitru vo, right? And presumably even though the רמב"ם Rambam is not
clear about it, here they give lashes and then they warn him
again. Okay, so he's first given physical lashes and a warning, and
then the next act of defiance, which shows that he's really rebelling
against their authority, that then leads to him getting stoned. Okay. All
right, so let's take a look. היה אחד מהן, hayah echad mehen,
מתרין בפני שלושה, matrin bifnei shlosha, ומלקין אותו, umalkin oto, חזר וקלקל,
נידון בעשרים ושלושה. chazar vekilkel nidon b'esrim ushlosha. Then you have a
בית דין beit din of 23, right, because that's a then it
becomes a capital crime. ואינו נסקל עד שיהיו שם שלושה ראשונים, ve'eino
niskal ad she'yihyu sham shlosha rishonim, שנאמר she'ne'emar בנינו זה, b'neinu ze,
זה שלקה בפניכם. ze shelakah bifneichem. So you need the three, apparently
when he was here was in front of a בית דין beit
din because you're administering lashes. Okay, so here this was a בית
דין beit din of three and this was a בית דין beit
din. of 23. So since here they say בנינו זה סורר ומורה,
b'neinu ze soreir umoreh, זה, ze, the same one that you know
earlier we had a problem with, so it has to be through
the three that were on this בית דין beit din, have to
be part of that בית דין. beit din, Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says שמע מינה, shma mina, בעינן קרא כדכתיב. ba'inan kra kideichtiv.
Since you need them to have exactly the way it says: grabbing
him, taking him, listening, etc. It's not enough that it's like we
don't assume the פסוקים are just sort of describing a classic case,
a standard case. No, it has to be exactly that and any
variation, if they can't speak, if they're missing an arm, or whatever,
any variation would invalidate it. So that's actually generally the debate, how
literally do we interpret those things? So should we learn from this
that that's the general rule, that we interpret these things literally? No.
שאני הכא, shani hacha, here it's different, דכולא קרא יתירא הוא. d'kula
kra yeitira hu. The whole thing is extra. Could have just said,
you know, that they stone him. Why does it give the whole
narrative to tell you it has to be exactly this? All right.
ומלקין בפני שלושה, umalkin bifnei shlosha, you warn in front of three.
למה לי? lamah li? בתרי סגי? bitrei sagi? What do you mean?
Any evidence that you bring against him is with two witnesses. What
does it mean in front of three? אמר אביי הכי קאמר, amar
Abaye hachi ka'amar, מתרין בו בפני שניים matrin bo bifnei shnayim ומלקין
אותו בפני שלושה. umalkin oto bifnei shlosha. So the lashes that are
administered for this act of stealing and eating and drinking, which by
the way, right, is not an act that you'd normally get lashes
for, but in this context it is, everything is out of proportion.
So then you have to bring witnesses that he stole from us,
ate and drank, etc., and then that's a court case of lashes
in front of three. So the lashes are in front of three
but the warning that they give him, interestingly, against the משנה mishna?
where it sounded like the warning occurred in the same context in
the presence of the בית דין, beit din since we learn them
both from the word וייסרו, veyisru, you could understand why it all
has to come at the same time, like we're you know making
a point of our authority here. But the גמרא says no, only
the lashes require בית דין, beit din. the warning can occur before
in front of witnesses, two witnesses, not three. Okay, so now the
גמרא says like this: מלקות בבן סורר ומורה היכא כתיבא? malkut b'ven
soreir umoreh heicha ktiva? Where is this idea of lashes? כדרבי אבהו.
k'd'rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי אבהו, d'amar rabbi Abbahu, למדנו וייסרו מן וייסרו.
lamadnu veyisru min veyisru. It says וייסרו veyisru from the case of
the מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. It says that if a
guy was lying they should afflict him, and we learn that that
means lashes. How do we know that that means lashes? From the
וייסרו veyisru of בן ben. סורר sorer ומורה. Where do we learn
it from בן ben, סורר ומורה? מן בן, min ben, from the
case of the בן. ben בן מן בן. ben min ben. And
the בן סורר ומורה from בן הכות הרשע. bin hakot harasha. The
classic וורט vort that we learn, והיה אם בן הכות הרשע, vehayah
im bin hakot harasha, והפילו לפניו והכהו vehipilo l'fanav vehikahu whatever, כדי
רשעתו במספר. kdei rish'ato b'mispar. So the classic פסוק pasuk about lashes
is from the word בין bin or בן, so that makes us
learn that the בן that the lashes, that the וייסרו veyisru of
בן סורר ומורה is lashes. והיה אם בן הכות הרשע, vehayah im
bin hakot harasha, fine. חזר וקלקל chazar vekilkel, נידון בעשרים ושלושה. nidon
b'esrim ushlosha. He went back and did it, it's a בית דין
beit din of 23. היינו דאיצטריכא ליה hainu d'itztaricha leih because it
says בנינו זה, b'neinu ze, so it has to be, include the
same three that were here have to be in this בית דין.
beit din. The one you know from earlier. So it says, but
don't we need the זה ze to tell you זה ולא סומים,
ze velo sumim, they can't be blind, they have to point to
be able to identify him by sight? No. אם כן לכתוב בנינו
הוא. im ken lichtov b'neinu hu. הוא, hu, he is our son.
מאי בנינו זה? mai b'neinu ze? This one. שמע מינה תרתי, shma
mina tarti, that the בית דין also has to recognize the son
and it has to be the same בית דין. Okay, so I'll
just read one רש"י Rashi and we'll end with this for now.
But just the רש"י Rashi on the התראה hatra'ah is important. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi, בפני שניים. bifnei shnayim. No, one minute.
No, no, not that one. There was another רש"י Rashi that just
explained what the התראה hatra'ah was. Hold on, maybe it was on
the משנה? mishna One minute. Yeah, if you just look, I just
want to read you the רש"י Rashi on the משנה just turning
to דף ע"א עמוד א'. daf ayin alef amud alef. We'll end
with this. רש"י Rashi says מתרין בו, matrin bo, they gave him
התראה. hatra'ah. So רש"י Rashi just clarifies this מתרין matrin is not
like the— get lashes unless you violate after following a warning. The
התראה hasraah is because that would normally require the witnesses to give
the התראה hasraah and here it's the parents that are giving the
התראה. hasraah. The מוסרין masrin here is not the warning in order
to enable the lashes. The התראה hasraah is to be איננו שומע
בקולנו einenu shomea b'kolenu. to assert that this is our parental authority
and then he's going to go violate. Okay, ועוד זו ספק התראה
הוא אם עובר הוא אם לאו, v'od zu safek hasraah hu im
over hu im lav, שלא מיד בשניהם עובר. shelo miyad bishneihem over.
The giving of the התראה hasraah here and then it's only later
that he goes out and he does the whole thing again and
is being stoned. So this warning is not, "don't you do it
again or else you're going to get stoned." It's not the classic
התראה hasraah to allow the punishment. Remember, the whole punishment anyway doesn't
follow normal rules. It's sort of seen, which is interesting, right? It's
not like before he does it you say, "hey, if you eat
that meat you're going to be חייב מיתה chayav misa as a
בן סורר ומורה," like presumably we don't need that type of התראה.
hasraah. שלא מיד בשניהם עובר אלא בסתר לאחר זמן הוא עושה, shelo
miyad bishneihem over ela b'seser l'achar zman hu oseh, אלא מוכיחין אותו.
ela mochiachin oso. The point is that they give them like as
parents, they basically give them מוסר. mussar. דבעינן ויסרו אותו, d'ba'inan v'yisru
oso, שלא ירגיל. shelo yargil. We don't want to see you ever
doing this again. ואם לא שמע מלקין אותו בבית דין, v'im lo
shama malkin oso b'veit din, ויליף לה מויסרו אותו. v'yalif la mi'v'yisru
oso. This רש"י Rashi by the way makes it sound a little
different. Makes it sound like the התראה hasraah appeared before the lashes.
Right? It says first they warned and then he defies them, which
makes more sense, right? איננו שומע einenu shomea. בקולנו. איננו שומע. This
רש"י Rashi makes it sound like there was some warning up here
that he was violating and because of that, violating the warning. But
anyway the point is, A, the warning is not התראה hasraah to
allow to give a punishment. This whole thing sort of violates those
normal rules. It sounds like you even wouldn't need normal התראה hasraah
for בן סורר ומורה. It is the parents saying you've got to
listen to us. And it's an interesting question whether it occurs up
here or does it only occur over here before the second occurrence
of that event. Exactly, right. Only in front of עדים. eidim. עדים
eidim to prove that he had those, that he was warned, and
he still went and he defied. Okay. All right, lot of fun,
right? Whether we're going to catch up or
not is
a different
story.